Inventory of the Jack Adelbert Killalee papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jack Adelbert Killalee papers
1927-1958
2014C36
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes (1.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, diaries, memoranda, reports, notes, personal documents, and photographs, relating to American technical assistance to Turkey and to highway construction in Turkey, Lebanon and elsewhere.
Killalee, Jack Adelbert, 1899-1957.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2014.
Access
The collection is open for research. The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Related Materials
Jack A. Killalee papers, Burlingame Historical Society, Burlingame, California
Biographical note
1899 Born, San Francisco, California
1917-1919 U.S. Army service
1925 B.S., University of California, Berkeley
1925-1955 Highway engineer, U.S. Bureau of Public Roads
1943 Alcan (Alaska-Canada) Highway construction engineer
1947-1950 Assistant division engineer, U.S. Public Roads Administration Group, Turkey
1955-1957 Consulting engineer, Tippetts-Abbett-McCarthy-Stratton Company, Lebanon
1957 Died, Burlingame, California
Scope and Contents note
The career of Jack A. Killalee as a United States government highway engineer was notable for its international dimension. After many years of activity in planning and constructing highways in the United States, he took part in an early Marshall Plan project to build highways in Turkey from 1947 to 1950. This was an instance of the far-flung work of the U.S. Economic Cooperation Administration in aiding in post-World War II reconstruction and development in many countries. After retiring from the U.S. Bureau of Public Roads in 1955, Killalee returned to the Middle East as a consulting engineer with the Tippetts-Abbett-McCarthy-Stratton Company, which was employed under a U.S. Foreign Operations Administration contract to plan and build a highway from Beirut, Lebanon, to Damascus, Syria. He was also involved with proposals for further highway construction in Jordan.
While the collection is small, it provides representative documentation of American international assistance and of the practicalities of life for Americans engaged in such assistance abroad. Many photographs of highway work are incorporated in textual reports in the collection.
Killalee maintained a permanent residence in Burlingame, California, and his papers were deposited with the Burlingame Historical Society after his death. The Hoover Institution received those of his papers focusing on his international work from the Burlingame Historical Society in 2014. Other Killalee papers remain with that Society.
United States. Bureau of Public Roads.; Engineers.; Highway engineering.; Roads--Lebanon; Roads--Turkey.; Technical assistance, American.
Collection Contents
- Biographical File, 1927-1958. (Box 1)
  Letters, obituaries and miscellany re Jack A. Killalee
  - General. Letters, genealogical notes and miscellany, 1927-1929 and undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Obituaries, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- U.S. Bureau of Public Roads File, 1931-1955. (Box 1)
  Diaries, correspondence, reports, memoranda and miscellany re work of Jack A. Killalee for the U.S. Bureau of Public Roads
  - General. Retirement letter of appreciation from Secretary of Commerce Sinclair Weeks and memoranda, 1950-1955 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Diaries re highway work in California and neighboring states (Box 1)
    - 1931 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - 1932 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Alcan (Alaska-Canada) Highway. Letters, organization chart, printed article and memorabilia, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Visiting foreign engineers. Bound folder of letters, reports and photographs re visits of engineers from various countries to Bureau of Public Roads headquarters in San Francisco, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Visiting Indian engineers. Bound folder of letters, reports and photographs re visits of engineers from India to Bureau of Public Roads headquarters in San Francisco, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- U.S. Public Roads Administration Group, Turkey, File, 1947-1950. (Box 2-3)
  Diary, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter and photographs re work of Jack A. Killalee for the U.S. Public Roads Administration Group in Turkey
  - General. Letters, memoranda and miscellany, 1948-1949. (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Includes Palace of Nations (Geneva) brochure
  - Diary, 1949 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Directory of U.S. government personnel in Turkey, 1949 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - La Quinzaine d'Ankara. Serial issues (Box 2)
    - 1948 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - 1949 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Bound scrapbook folders of telegrams, clippings, memorabilia and photographs, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 2: 6-7)
  - Photographs of scenes in Ankara and of highway work, ca. 1947-1950 (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
- Tippetts-Abbett-McCarthy-Stratton Company File, 1954-1957. (Box 3-4)
  Diary, correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed matter and photographs re work of Jack A. Killalee for the Tippetts-Abbett-McCarthy-Stratton Company in Lebanon
  - Diary, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, 1954-1957. (Box-folder 3: 4)
    Includes business contracts and list of American evacuees from Beirut at time of Suez War (1956)
  - Highway materials testing. Correspondence, memoranda, reports, charts and photographs, 1955-1957. (Box-folder 3: 5-6)
    Includes material on work of Highway Materials Laboratory near Beirut
  - Jordan highway proposal. Correspondence, memoranda, notes, map and printed matter, 1956, re proposed highway in Jordan from Amman to Aqaba (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - U.S. Operations Mission, Lebanon, reports, 1954-1957 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Printed matter. Clippings, serial issues and Arabic-English dictionary, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 4: 3-4)
  - Miscellany. Business cards, lists, notes and diagram, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 4: 5-6)
  - Photographs, 1955 and undated (Box-folder 4: 7)